Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Hans Ihlefeld Papers, 1952-1980, bulk 1972-1978
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Hans Ihlefeld papers 1952-1980, bulk 1972-1978
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office.
13.5 linear feet Extent: 12,150 Items
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Hans Ihlefeld was financial manager and director of JWT's branch offices in Frankfurt, Vienna and Zurich in the 1960s and 1970s. The Hans Ihlefeld Papers document Ihlefeld's tenure as financial manager and director of the Frankfurt, Vienna, and Zurich offices of JWT, where he oversaw the expansion of the agency with regard to number of clients, subsidiaries, and financial volume. The collection includes correspondence, telexes and telegrams, memoranda, tables of results, charts and graphs, client and account lists, profit plans, computer printouts, invoices and receipts, contracts, clippings, articles and other printed material. Specific topics documented in the Hans Ihlefeld papers include financial statements and transactions concerning the German-speaking areas of Europe (Germany, Austria, and Switzerland) and Scandinavia, especially profit projections and periodic (monthly, quarterly, and annual) results reports; communication between Ihlefeld and other JWT executives and offices about JWT short- and long-term strategy; account planning; communication with JWT's European subsidiaries ARC, Basisresearch, Century, ProService, and PR; and correspondence with clients. The bulk of communications take place between the Vienna, Zurich, Stockholm, and New York offices. Notable company correspondents include Peter Gilow and Harry Clark. Clients well documented in the collection include Braun, Unilever (Elida Gibbs, Lever Sunlicht), Ford, Jacobs, Kraft, and PepsiCo. Approximately 60% of the collection is in German, and the remainder is in English, except for one very small portion in French.
RL.00698
Language: Material in English, German, French
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office. Hans Ihlefeld Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1995.
Biographical Note
1969 Joined JWT
1973 Financial Manager for Vienna and Zurich, JWT Frankfurt
1977 Director for Germany, JWT Frankfurt
Collection Overview
The Hans Ihlefeld Papers span the years 1969 to 1978, with the bulk of the material dating from 1972 to 1978, and document Ihlefeld's tenure as financial manager and director of the Frankfurt, Vienna, and Zurich offices of JWT, where he oversaw the expansion of the agency with regard to number of clients, subsidiaries, and financial volume. The collection includes correspondence, telexes and telegrams, memoranda, tables of results, charts and graphs, client and account lists, profit plans, computer printouts, invoices and receipts, contracts, clippings, articles and other printed material. Specific topics documented in the Hans Ihlefeld papers include: financial statements and transactions concerning the German-speaking areas of Europe (Germany, Austria, and Switzerland) and Scandinavia, especially profit projections and periodic (monthly, quarterly, and annual) results reports; communication between Ihlefeld and other JWT executives and offices about JWT short- and long-term strategy; account planning; communication with JWT's European subsidiaries ARC, Basisresearch, Century, ProService, and PR; and correspondence with clients. The bulk of communications take place between the Vienna, Zurich, Stockholm, and New York offices. Notable correspondents include Peter Gilow and Harry Clark. Clients well documented in the collection include Braun, Unilever (Elida Gibbs, Lever Sunlicht), Ford, Jacobs, Kraft, and PepsiCo. Approximately 60% of the collection is in German, and the remainder is in English, except for one very small portion in French.
The collection is made up of three series: Correspondence and Memoranda; Finance; and German-Speaking Areas (GSA) Series.
The Correspondence and Memoranda Series comprises reports, summaries and written communications that passed through Ihlefeld's office. The series is organized into six subseries--General Correspondence, Clients, JWT Offices, JWT Subsidiaries, Memoranda/Haus Mitteilungen, and Trend Letter. The General Correspondence Subseries focuses primarily on the Frankfurt Office's financial negotiations and agreements with clients in the form of letters, budgets (of media and production costs), billings, and taxes. The Clients Subseries reflects the financial and planning aspects of JWT-Frankfurt's relationship with its clients. The Ford account in particular is well-documented, but files also exist for other clients including Braun, Jacobs, PepsiCo, and Unilever. The JWT Offices Subseries documents the coordination of financial operations between the Frankfurt Office and the Zurich, Stockholm, Vienna, and New York offices, and to a lesser extent with other JWT offices. Topics include short- and long-term financial planning (particularly with regard to profits and taxes), transactions between different JWT offices, tax audits, insurance matters, legal matters, and personnel matters (including visits) in the Frankfurt, Vienna, Zurich, and Stockholm offices. The JWT Subsidiaries Subseries gives information--mostly of a financial or tax-related nature--on JWT's European subsidiaries ARC, Basis, Century, ProService, and PR. The Memoranda/Haus-Mitteilungen Subseries documents the daily administration of the Frankfurt office, particularly with regard to production, financial matters, personnel, and taxes. The Trend Letter Subseries documents the acquisition and demise of Trend Letter, a financial newsletter designed for the business side of the advertising industry.
The Finance Series documents gains and losses, budgeting, taxes, the role of the comptroller, and monthly, quarterly, as well as annual results in the German Speaking Area.
The German-Speaking Area (GSA) Series documents JWT operations in the three-country area of Germany, Austria, and Switzerland. Topics include financial reporting and planning in the GSA and Scandinavia, as well as for several European subsidiaries.
Related Material:
For related materials, see other collections in the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives, especially the papers of other Frankfurt office executives in the Frankfurt Office Records, Such as the Harry Clark Papers and the Peter Gilow Papers. Additional information may be found in the Frankfurt Advertisements Collection, the JWT Newsletter Collection, JWT Writings and Speeches Collection, and the Frankfurt Film and Video Collection.
Subject Headings
J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Stockholm Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Vienna Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Zürich Office; Unilever (Firm); Ford Motor Company; Kraft Foods Company; PepsiCo, Inc.; Clark, Harry, 1935-; Gilow, Peter, 1918-1992; Ihlefeld, Hans; Advertising -- Europe; Advertising -- Scandinavia; Advertising agencies -- Scandinavia; Advertising agencies -- Scandinavia -- History; Advertising agencies -- Accounting; Advertising agencies -- Europe; Advertising agencies -- Europe -- History; Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising executives; Clippings; Contracts; Memoranda; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence and Memoranda Series, 1967-1980, bulk 1972-1978, (5 boxes)
  - General Correspondence Subseries, 1973-1978
    Contains typed and handwritten letters, notes, memoranda, and other documents. The most prominent correspondent is Manfred Ostwald of the JWT Frankfurt office, but several other JWT and corporate correspondents are also present. Referenced clients include Champion, De Beers, Johnson, Kaufhof, Kellogg's, Lever-Sunlicht, and Wick. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1973-1978, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Clients Subseries, 1974-1978
    Consists of typed and handwritten letters, telexes and telegrams, invoices, charts, notes, memoranda (Haus-Mitteilungen), contracts, fee agreements, call reports (Kontaktberichte), and file memos (Aktennotizen) concerning all aspects of account planning for JWT-Frankfurt, and to some extent of JWT-Vienna. Divided into three sections: account planning (thereunder by office), Ford of Europe (thereunder chronologically), and other clients (thereunder alphabetically) While a large part of the series records the financial transactions between the partners, another section of letters details the responsibilities of JWT as an advertising agency, the assessment of fees, and the future of the German-speaking area. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Account Planning (Box 1)
      - Frankfurt, 1974-1978, (10 folders) (Box 1)
      - Vienna, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Braun, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Ford ESO, 1974-1979, (5 folders) (Box 1)
    - Other clients, 1977, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      Includes Burger King, DeBeers, Elida, Pepsi, Seagram, and Teledyne Water Pik.
  - JWT Offices Subseries, 1971-1980
    Chiefly Hans Ihlefeld's correspondence with JWT international offices, especially Vienna, Zurich, London, New York, and Stockholm. The series contains typed and hand-written letters, telexes and telegrams, printed material, notes, memoranda, clippings and articles, minutes, reports, charts and graphs, questionnaires, receipts, contracts, quarterly results, profit plans, account lists, and other documents concerning JWT's financial operations--from international tax planning to individual offices. Issues specifically noted in the series include accounts, tax planning, growth and investments. Important correspondents include Peter Horak (JWT-Zurich), John Novotny and Håkan Verner-Carlsson (both JWT-Stockholm), Alfred Tiefenbrunner (JWT-Vienna), Ed Lanzo (JWT-New York), and Manfred Ostwald (JWT-Frankfurt). Clients and products mentioned in this series include DeBeers, Elida, Ford, Gilette, Jacobs, Kodak, Kraft, PanAm, PepsiCo, Sunlicht, and Unilever. Arranged alphabetically by office, preceded by a folder of general documents.
    - General, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Amsterdam, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
    - Brussels, 1973, 1975, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Buenos Aires, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Chicago, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Copenhagen, 1972-1978 (Box 2)
    - Detroit, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Istanbul, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Johannesburg, 1974, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Lisbon, 1975 (Box 2)
    - London, 1970-1978, (5 folders) (Box 2)
    - Los Angeles, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Madrid, 1973, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
    - Milan, 1972-1978 (Box 2)
    - New York, 1971-1978, (12 folders) (Box 2)
    - Paris, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
    - Rio de Janeiro, 1978 (Box 2)
    - San Juan, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Stockholm
      - General, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1973-1978, (6 folders) (Box 2)
      - Kreatörerna, 1977 (Box 2)
      - Lagerlöf, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
      - Monthly Telexes, 1973-1977 (Box 3)
      - Price Waterhouse, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
      - Profit Plans, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
      - Quarterly Results, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
    - Sydney, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Toronto, 1972, 1974, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Vienna
      - General, 1971-1977, (4 folders) (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1977, (5 folders) (Box 3)
      - Hamtil, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
      - Haus-Mitteilungen, 1977 (Box 3)
      - Marketing plan, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Monthly telexes, 1971-1977, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      - Profit Plan, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
      - Quarterly Results, 1972-1975, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Statistics, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - Zurich
      - Banks, 1973-1974, 1977, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1972-1977, (1-2 of 9 folders) (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1972-1977, (3-9 of 9 folders) (Box 4)
      - FIDES, 1971-1977, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Ford Audit, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Meetings, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Monthly Telexes, 1971-1977, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Profit Plan, 1971-1975 (Box 4)
      - Quarterly Results, 1971-1977, (3 folders) (Box 4)
      - Statistics, 1969-1978 (Box 4)
  - JWT Subsidiaries Subseries, 1967-1980, bulk 1972-1978
    Contracts, monthly statements, typed and hand-written letters, telexes and telegrams, notes, charts, profit plans, audit reports, quarterly reports, printed material, minutes, and other documents pertaining to JWT's European subsidiaries ARC, Basisresearch, Century, ProService, and PR. Arranged alphabetically by subsidiary.
    - ARC (Box 4)
      - General, 1973-1978, (3 folders) (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 4)
      - Finance, 1971-1974 (Box 4)
      - Verträge, 1971-1976 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Basisresearch
      - General, 1972-1978 (Box 4)
      - Monthly Statements, 1971-1976 (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Profit Plan, 1972-1975 (Box 5)
      - Quarterly Results, 1972-1975 (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Century
      - General, 1974-1977 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1967-1980, (2 folders) (Box 5)
        - FIDES, 1968-1979, (2 folders) (Box 5)
        - FIDES, Vieli, 1973-1979 (Box 5)
      - Finance
        - 1974-1980, (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - Generalversammlungen, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
      - Protokolle, 1975-1978 (Box 5)
      - Shares/Verträge, 1972-1975 (Box 5)
      - Transactions, 1975-1979 (Box 5)
      - Urkunden, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - PR
      - General, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - ProService
      - General, 1972-1978 (Box 5)
      - Monthly Statements, 1971-1976 (Box 5)
      - Quarterly Results, 1972-1975, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Memoranda/Haus-Mitteilungen Subseries, 1972-1978, bulk 1975-1978
    Documents the daily administration of the Frankfurt office, particularly with regard to production, financial matters, personnel, and taxes. Includes the 1978 Management Style Diagnosis Test from the Norman H. Strouse Seminar and a 1978 document titled Kommunikationsmonitor, published by JWT subsidiary Basisresearch (both in the 1977-1978 folder). Correspondents include Burkhard Schwarz, Tilman Mauser, Peter Gilow, Manfred Ostwald, Paul Siebel, and Heinz Möckel. Important clients represented include Ford and Glücksklee. Arranged alphabetically.
    - General, 1972-1978, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - Finance, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - H+D, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Internationale Gruppe, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Unit 1, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Unit 2, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Unit 3, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Vorschlagswesen, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Trend Letter Subseries, 1975-1979, bulk 1976-1978
    Correspondence, reports, newsletters and other publications document the history of the short-lived publication, Trend Letter. Originally founded by Bernd Rohrbach to address the business side of the advertising industry, Trend Letter ran into financial difficulties and transformed into a limited liability company with Rohrbach, JWT, and Basisresearch holding one third of the company each. By the end of 1976, however, Trend Letter was discontinued, but Rohrbach and JWT continued to fight over the outstanding debts for the next three years. The series documents JWT's dealings with Rohrbach and Trend Letter, from the initial proposition by Rohrbach to the demise of the newsletter, including Rohrbach's original concept for the newsletter; internal memos confirming the interest in, and need for, such a newsletter; and letters to prospective subscribers and discussions that led to discontinue publication. Correspondents include Bernd Rohrbach and Peter Gilow. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Correspondence, 1975-1979, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Newsletter, 1976 (Box 5)
- Finance Series, 1952-1977, bulk 1965-1975, (3 boxes)
  Contains budgets, memoranda, notes, charts, lists, graphs, telexes, typed letters, computer printouts and other documents concerning the financial transactions of JWT in the German-speaking area. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Budgets (Box 6)
    - General, 1952-1972, (16 folders) (Box 6)
    - Basisresearch, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Frankfurt, 1967-1971, (7 folders) (Box 6)
    - GSA
      - General, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      - Memoranda, 1967-1968, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Statistics, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Vienna, 1967-1971, (5 folders) (Box 7)
    - Zurich, 1967-1971, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Financial Reporting
    - Exchange Rates, 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - London, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - New York, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - GWA-Betriebsvergleich, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Memoranda, 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - Monthly Assessment
    - General, 1971-1974, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Frankfurt, 1970-1971 (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Vienna, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - Zurich, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Monthly Telexes
    - General, 1972-1977, (5 folders) (Box 7)
    - ARC, 1977 (Box 7)
    - Basisresearch, 1977 (Box 7)
    - Century, 1977 (Box 7)
    - ProService, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Operating Results
    - Correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 7)
    - Frankfurt, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
    - International, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
    - Stockholm, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
    - Vienna, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
    - Zurich, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
  - Profit Plan, 1972-1975, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Quarterly Results, 1970-1975, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - Statistics, 1970-1975, (2 folders) (Box 8)
- German-Speaking Area (GSA) Series, 1976-1980, (2 boxes)
  Contains monthly telexes, profit plans, reports, three-year plans, notes, charts, computer printouts, typed correspondence, and other documents pertaining to financial reporting and planning of JWT in Germany, Austria, Switzerland and Scandinavia as well as to the subsidiaries ARC, Basisresearch, Century, PR, and ProService. In German and English. Arranged alphabetically.
  - General, 1976-1977 (Box 8)
  - Monthly Telexes
    - ARC, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Basisresearch, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Frankfurt, 1978 (Box 8)
    - PR, 1978 (Box 8)
    - ProService, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Stockholm, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Vienna, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Zurich, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Profit Plans
    - General, 1978 (Box 8)
    - ARC, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Basisresearch, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Ford ESO, 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - Frankfurt, 1976-1978 (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - PR, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - ProService, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Stockholm, 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - Vienna, 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - Zurich, 1976-1978 (Box 8)
  - Quarterly Results
    - General, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - ARC, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Basisresearch, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Ford ESO, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Frankfurt, 1976-1978 (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - PR, 1978 (Box 9)
    - ProService, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Stockholm, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
    - Vienna, 1976-1978 (Box 9)
    - Zurich, 1976-1978, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Three-year plan, 1977-1978 (Box 9)